<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Dulcedo ex acerbis. Sound doctrine from the errors contained in Mr. Keith's sermons and apologies. / By a member of the Church of England. O D M T.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1700</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 98 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B02800</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D2517A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R174771</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">47012404</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 47012404</idno>
            <idno type="VID">174373</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B02800)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 174373)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2686:21)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Dulcedo ex acerbis. Sound doctrine from the errors contained in Mr. Keith's sermons and apologies. / By a member of the Church of England. O D M T.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>24 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1700.]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place and date of publication taken from Wing (2nd ed.)</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: stained, with loss of text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Keith, George, 1639?-1716.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  History --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Sermons --  History and criticism --  England --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:174373:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Dulcedo ex Acerbis.</hi> Sound DOCTRINE from the ERRORS Contained in Mr. Keith's Sermons AND APOLOGIES. The Second EDITION.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>ZACH. 13. 4.</bibl>And it ſhall come to paſs in the days of true Chriſtians, that the Prophets ſhall be aſhamed of their Viſions: Nor ſhall they wear any more a rough Garment, (a black Cloak, a broad Hat, a ſhort Cravat, and Fryar's Hoods) to deceive.</q>
            <p>By a Member of the Church of <hi>England. ODMT.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="tract">
            <p n="1">1. THS Paper having fully made out and demonſtrated in its former Edition, that Mr. <hi>Keith</hi> doth labour under ſeveral miſtakes; and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandeth neither Scripture nor Divinity, nor the ground of Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, to wit, Regeneration by the Power from on High, which is the Spiritual word in the Heart; not the outward; I was in hope he would, ſince he is ſo apt to turn and forſake his old Errors, have given Glory to God, and ſhewed by ſome publick Act, or Recantation Sermon, that he is really aſham'd of his Viſions, and his Zeal for a Doctrine exploded, and proved juſt oppoute to that of the Apoſtles. But <hi>Luſcis Lux oculis nocuit,</hi> it is Darkneſs which the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:174373:2"/> World is in <hi>love</hi> with. <hi>Joh.</hi> 3. 19. In vain I expected ſuch Man as Mr. <hi>Keith,</hi> who runs from the Light within, ſhould ſo ſoon ſtop his carreer and freely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to it: He is too far gone from it; and it is to be feared, as ſhall be ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed more at large; he is become one of thoſe that rebel againſt the Light be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they do not know it. <hi>Joh.</hi> 24. 13. and ſeek for the praiſe of Men more than for that comes from God. <hi>Joh.</hi> 5. 44. 12. 42, 43. Therefore ſeeing no great hopes (tho' he be always Learning) of his coming to the Truth. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 7. and ſeeing that far from it, he goes on unconcerned, Preaching another Goſpel than the Apoſtles Preached; ſetting up the outward Word above the Light and guidance of God's Spirit within Man, aſcribing the ſecond Birth, or the Regeneration, againſt the poſitive words of Chriſt, <hi>Joh.</hi> 3. 5. to the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward word; and like they that Chriſt ſpeaks of, <hi>Matth.</hi> 23. 15. and the Horſe in the white Robe, <hi>Revel. 6. 2. Conquering and to Conquer;</hi> and bragging of his Succeſs (the unjuſt Man knows no Shame, <hi>Zeph.</hi> 3. 5. and is very confident <hi>Prov.</hi> 14. 16.) I will, tho' no Quaker nor admirer of Quakeriſm, ſmite this ſcorner of the Light, that the ſimple may beware and come to underſtanding. <hi>Ch.</hi> 19. 25. and go on as well as he in Printing a ſecond time; and bear wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to the Light once more before great and ſmall, tho' the <hi>Great Men</hi> rage with him, <hi>Jerem.</hi> 5. 5. that Truth may triumph at laſt, and that neither Mr. <hi>Keith's</hi> nor the Quakers Opinions may have the better of it.
<q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Devant les Rois &amp; Grands Siegneurs dis monde</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ton temoignage, O Dieu, jannonceray</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sans que jamais vergongne me confonde.</hi>
                  </l> 
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. 46.</bibl>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. I thought that between both the Quakers and the Churchmen ſome Anſwer might have been fram'd, and that the Spiritual Men, or the Children of the Light would have appeared for Truth, and had Diſcretion enough to put Mr. <hi>Keith</hi> to Shame. <hi>Judg.</hi> 18 7. and ſo waited for their words, as <hi>Elibu, Job</hi> 32. 7, 11. but in vain; for when I had waited whilſt they ſearch'd out what to ſay, and behold none anſwered nor convinced Mr. <hi>Keith V.</hi> 12. being as wiſe as he is, becauſe they think they are wiſe, <hi>Joh.</hi> 9. 41. <hi>Jerem.</hi> 8. 8, 9, I was forced at laſt to take the buſineſs in hand, and to ſhew my Opinion in the behalf of the Truth. <hi>There is a Spirit in Man;</hi> and (without being Quaker Enthuſiaſt or Fanatick) it is, by Mr. <hi>Keith's</hi> leave, <hi>the inſpiration of God gives underſtanding for that, Job</hi> 32. 8, 17.</p>
            <p n="3">3. To make good my charge againſt Mr. <hi>Keith,</hi> I have need of no more than what he ſaith pag. 6. of his Farewel or Abjuration Sermon. <hi>That Faith is wrought in us by means of the written word: That is to ſay, by the Doctrine of Chriſt Crucified as it is Preached to us. For as the Scriptures ſay, Faith cometh by hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and hearing by the word</hi> (the Text ſaith the word <hi>of God, Rom.</hi> 10. 17. which laſt Word he takes away <hi>Revel.</hi> 22. 19. the better to put his blind Conſtruction upon the Simple, and to ſhew the wiſer Sort what a faithful Miniſter of God's Word he is become) <hi>And that Word,</hi> continues he, <hi>is the outward Word in the Mouth of the Preachers; as it follows, V.</hi> 14. (whereas this ſame <hi>V.</hi> 14 going before the words which he cites from the 17th. it ſhould be as it preceeds, but to ſay as it follows, makes the conſequence he draws look better and more plauſible.) <hi>And how ſhall they hear without a Preacher? And hence the Word even the Doctrinal Word, is called the Incorruptible Seed, of which true Believers are Regenerated and Born again, according to, 1 Pet.</hi> 1. 23. Theſe are Mr. <hi>Keith's</hi> own words; and what he, and, as it ſeems, his Party call ſound Doctrine.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:174373:2"/>
            <p n="4">4. But that is not the Doctrine of the true Church of England; for it is not that of Chriſt, nor of St. <hi>Peter</hi> himſelf; for his very Words themſelves ſhew plainly that this is falſe. His Words in the ſaid place are, <hi>being Born again, not of Corruptible Seed, but of Incorruptible, by the Word of God, which Lives, and Abideth for Ever.</hi> From which any man that reads, may ſee that the Word meant here, is the Word of God Himſelf; and that it being God's Word, and ſuch Word as is Living and Abiding for Ever, it is not the outward word in the Mouth of the Preachers; for that is the Preacher's word; and is not liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, but dead, nay a Letter that killeth. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. 6. or at leaſt that leaves one dead, in the ſtate it finds one in; Endureth but for a while in the hearts of ſome hearers. <hi>Math.</hi> 13. 21. Was not from the beginning, and therefore will have an end. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. 8. Serving but till the Inward ariſe and ſhine in the heart. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 19. And in fine, is not that which worketh true Faith in the Saints, nor which they are Born again and Regenerated of: ſeeing ſome have Believed, (as the Wiſe Men of the Eaſt) and were Regenerated; (as <hi>Cornelius)</hi> without it: the Spirit (which is the thing that Regenerates the Saints <hi>John</hi> 3. 5.) falling upon him and thoſe many Friends he had with him; <hi>Act.</hi> 10. 24, 27. as ſoon as ever <hi>Peter</hi> had begun to ſpeak to them, <hi>V.</hi> 44. that is, before they had heard half of the Doctrine of Chriſt, and of all the Myſteries Mr. <hi>Keith</hi> enumerates at the foot of pag. 10. and by which he ſaith Faith comes: which they knew and beleived without doubt nevertheleſs; the Spirit <hi>teaching all things</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out hearing them Preached. <hi>Joh.</hi> 14 26.</p>
            <p n="5">5. And common Senſe ſhews the ſame. For it ſhews, that ſince this Word, which Mr. <hi>Keith</hi> argueth for, can't give ſo much as one Senſe, <hi>viz.</hi> Hearing to the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, much leſs can it give it all the Senſes, or the whole Life; and much leſs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get the Soul, or give it its Life again; nor that which comes from Hearing or Underſtanding, <hi>viz.</hi> Faith. And if for reading of Words, or for hearing them Preached, Men had Faith wrought in them, and were regenerated, it would follow, that all thoſe which heard Chriſt preach, believed: and that none of thoſe, who hear, Sermons, and read the Scripture, are unregenerated: and that all may be ſaved at the ſame cheap, eaſy rate, that Papiſts hope to be ſo; that is, for hearing Maſs ſaid, and ſome few Ave <hi>Maries</hi> cryed about them when they die. And Mr. <hi>Keith</hi> hath ill Luck to have met with ſo few Men that believe a he tells us, <hi>Pag.</hi> 12. of his <hi>Reaſons,</hi> among ſo many Hearers; for he reckons in that Place no more than 40 Perſons brought over by his Preaching, from Quakery to his Church.</p>
            <p n="6">6. So that the Word in the Mouth, being not that which begets, and work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth Faith in the Soul; it remains, that the inward ſpiritual Word in the Heart and Soul, is that which doth it; <hi>being quick and powerful, and ſharper than any Sword, piercing to the very Soul</hi> and inward Thoughts of the Heart. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 4. 12. (as <hi>Peter</hi> ſhewed it to be in the Caſe of <hi>Ananias,</hi> and of <hi>Sapphira</hi> his Wife, <hi>Act.</hi> 5. 3, 9.) to work powerfully there, and ſtir up all the Powers of the Soul and the Body. And this Word being Spirit and Life, as Chriſt himſelf ſaith. <hi>Joh.</hi> 6. 63. and a Spirit <hi>that giveth life and quickneth.</hi> 2 Cor. 3. 6. it is therefore the only Word that liveth and begets the Soul again; and it is, on this Account of being a Spiritual and a penetrating Word, repreſented by a Sword coming from the Mouth of Chriſt. <hi>Rev.</hi> 1. 16. and with ſome known by the Name of the Sword of the Spirit. <hi>Eph.</hi> 6. 17. And as it is that which was from the beginning with God; <hi>Joh.</hi> 1. 2. it is alſo that alone which abideth for ever.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:174373:3"/>
            <p n="7">7. The word of Faith which St. <hi>Paul</hi> and the Apoſtles preached, and by which they begat Souls, <hi>1 Cor. 4. 15. Jam. 1. 18.</hi> was inward and ſpiritual in the heart, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. 8. and a Spirit: for <hi>they were the Miniſters of the Spirit that gives Life, and not of the dead Letter,</hi> or outward word, <hi>that killeth.</hi> 2 Cor. 3 6. Miniſtring to that Spirit which Chriſt himſelf <hi>miniſtreth,</hi> Gal. 3. 5. that thereby Men might <hi>ſerve God in newneſs of the Spirit,</hi> and no <hi>more in the oldneſs of the Letter</hi> of Scripture. <hi>Rom. 7. 6. of the Doctrine of Baptiſms, of Repentance from dead works</hi> and other <hi>fundamentals,</hi> (as Mr. <hi>Keith</hi> doth call them, and recommend <hi>pag. 10.)</hi> of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian <hi>Religion, or of the Doctrine of Chriſt,</hi> which St. <hi>Paul</hi> exhorts <hi>to leave.</hi> Hebr. 6. 1, 2. and Mr. <hi>Keith</hi> to ſtick to. And they preached the Goſpel, which is the Power of God, <hi>Rom. 1. 16.</hi> and which being a Spirit, they begat Souls again by. <hi>1 Cor. 4. 15.</hi> This Power being the ſame as the <hi>Power from on high,</hi> which is the Holy Spirit, <hi>Luk. 24. 49. Act. 1 5, 8.</hi> and which regenerates Souls, <hi>Joh. 3. 5.</hi> So that the Word they preach'd, being Power and Spirit, it is not the empty Word in the Mouth of Mr. <hi>Keith:</hi> which they begat, or became Fathers in God to Souls with: but the inward ſpiritual powerful Word in the Heart of good Men, which they ſtirr'd up and ſet a working by that which they received of Chriſt, and which his Sheep heard therefore ſpeaking through their Heart and Mouth. <hi>John 10. 3, 5.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">8. If the Proteſtants become Fathers in God by preaching the written outward Word, why may not the Popiſh Prieſts be ſo too by their Preaching? But if Preachers become ſuch by Preaching and Miniſtring the ſpiritual Word of Truth, Pray to whom Fathers in God, and whoſe Miniſters are they that ſtand for an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other Word, and countenance its Preaching? It is ſtrange Fathers in God ſhould beget, they know not how, nor by what; and if they know, ſhould keep their Trades to themſelves, and ſhould not let Mr. <hi>Keith,</hi> who hath deſerv'd it ſo well at their hands, know the Knack on't! I am afraid Mr. <hi>Keith</hi> will never ſpoil a Biſhop, but always remain a Tool.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Quaere.</hi> Pray, Mr. Preacher, what's Religion now a-days? <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is nothing but Acting the Story of Chriſt: and a Cloak with as many Facings as Parties or Sects, for the Sophiſters of each to carry on their Deſigns; and for every Party to act their Non-ſenſe under impudently to the face of thoſe that know better things, as the ſilly Papiſts did their Maſs in King <hi>James</hi> his time. Poor King, to take his Prieſt-craft for a Religious Worſhip, and to be thus put upon in his moſt weighty Concern, by dull Souls, more confined and leſs knowing than him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. But tho' Kings pay dear for it, and have paid ſo ever ſince the time of <hi>Jereboam,</hi> who became a ſad Example of God's Juſtice upon ſuch. <hi>1 Kings 13. 34.</hi> Yet no Calves, no King prevails in the Mouth of their Profets and of their Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticians: who muſt have ſome Calviſh Prieſts. <hi>Ch. 12. 31.</hi> to preach a Calviſh Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, that is, fit for Calves only, and for making of Men Calves, that they may lead them like Calves: and will prevail to the End, whilſt Kings learn nothing from them of God judging in the Earth: <hi>Pſal. 58. 11.</hi> and diſpoſing of Kingdoms: <hi>giving them to whom he will, and ſetting up over them even the Baſeſt of Men.</hi> Dan. 4. 17. The Kings that knew God themſelves, not only ſerv'd him themſelves, but preached and reformed their Prieſts and Clergy themſelves. <hi>1. King. 8. 12, 14. 2 King. 23. 2. 2 Chron. 29. 5. Pſal. 51. 13. 119. 46.</hi> but all they that know him not, give their Power to the Beaſt. <hi>Rev. 17. 13.</hi> Kings might ſerve God by Proxy, if they had none of that Word in the Heart which all Men have, and could give God an account by their Prieſts and Favourites.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:174373:3"/>
            <p n="9">9. It is the Spirit gives life, quickneth. <hi>2 Cor. 3. 6. Joh. 6. 63.</hi> creates, forms, reforms, and upholds all things living. <hi>Gen. 1. 2. Pſal. 33. 6. 104. 30.</hi> and that begets Souls therefore. Without it all things lie dead, and return to their No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing. <hi>verſ. 29. Jam. 2. 26.</hi> and he is the conveyer of Life unto all Creatures: The hand and the arm of God. <hi>Joh. 12. 38.</hi> whereby he makes all his Works. From him the Firſt Man <hi>Adam</hi> received his <hi>Breath of Lives.</hi> Gen. 2. 7. that is, both of the Divine and of the Natural Life; (for note that the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Word is <hi>Chajim</hi> in the Plural, not <hi>Chajah,</hi> as it ſhould be to ſignify Breath of Life.) And as <hi>Adam</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the Life of his Soul from him, ſo from him we muſt get it again, and be born of it; not from the material Word, or dead Letter of Scripture. God's Kingdom, or Salvation, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, is through it. <hi>Rom. 14. 17.</hi> then we muſt be born again of it. <hi>Joh. 3. 5.</hi> and be born of God, and of this ſpiritual Seed, to have it remain in us. <hi>1 Joh. 3. 9.</hi> and have the Kingdom of God or life eternal in us. <hi>Luk. 17. 21.</hi> The Seed it ſelf which the Fleſh is born and begotten of, is a Spirit abſtracted from the Soul and the Body of Parents, which are but Men: Much more then that of the Soul regenerated of God, who is only a Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and the Father of Spirits. <hi>Joh. 4. 24. Hebr. 12. 9.</hi> ought to be a Spiritual, and not a Material Thing: ſuch as is the outward Word, which Mr. <hi>Keith</hi> ſoweth about in Sermons and in Papers; which Bookſellers and Printers catch at ſo nim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, and put <hi>Impune</hi> upon the World.</p>
            <p n="10">10. Now Chriſt himſelf is the word. Joh. 1. 1, 14. in the Heart and in the Mouth. <hi>Rom. 10. 9.</hi> and being that ſame Power of God, <hi>1 Cor. 1. 24.</hi> by which God made all, Joh. 1. 2, 3. (the World and all Things therein. <hi>Hebr. 1. 2.)</hi> and which upholdeth all things, <hi>v. 3.</hi> and gives them their Light and Life. Joh. 8. 12. 14. 6. it is he that begets Souls; and he is the ſame alſo as the Spirit or Power which hath been ſhew'd to doe it. Jeſus being the ſame Word as <hi>Paul</hi> ſpake of, <hi>v. 8.</hi> of <hi>Chap. 10.</hi> of <hi>Rom.</hi> and the ſame Power of God, <hi>1 Cor. 1. 24.</hi> as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith the Goſpel is, <hi>Rom. 1. 16. And the Lord is that Spirit,</hi> which <hi>Paul</hi> was Miniſter of, <hi>2 Cor. 3. 8, 16.</hi> and when the Holy Ghoſt comes it is Chriſt that comes Himſelf. Joh. 14. 16, 18. And upon the whole Matter, Chriſt being the Word of God that was from the Beginning, <hi>Chap. 1. 2.</hi> and by whom all things were made, and <hi>Emmanuel,</hi> God in us, <hi>Matth. 1. 23.</hi> dwelling in us for ever, according to his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe Joh. 14 17. except we be Reprobates. <hi>2 Cor. 13. 5.</hi> and the Holy Ghoſt himſelf; he is the Word in the Heart that abideth for ever; and of whom St. <hi>Peter</hi> meant the Faithful are born again. Being upon this account called the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> that is, the ſecond Father, or Begetter of Mankind: and the Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groom, infuſing his ſpiritual Seed in Man, and impregnating his Soul; which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes his Mother thereby; and by the ſame means he becomes the Son of Man, and is formed within Man. <hi>Gal. 4. 19.</hi> And in ſhort, Chriſt and the Word and the Spirit are all one,</p>
            <p n="11">11. And he is called the word (in Greek <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or Reaſon) becauſe he is Wiſdom, Light and Underſtanding, in God, in the World, and in the Soul. In God, he is the Wiſdom and the Power, <hi>1 Cor. 1. 24.</hi> Will and Act: For God having no Organs, as Mouth or Hands, his word is the thing it ſelf that is done by his Power and Wiſdom; and having no other Will than his Power and his Act, becauſe <hi>Voluntas,</hi> ſaith one, <hi>Conſilio naſcitur,</hi> and there is nothing but Sight, no thinking nor conſulting at all, in the moſt Wiſe God; his Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, Power, Will, Act, are all one, that is, his Word. In the World he is the Light, <hi>Joh. 8. 12.</hi> and the Spirit that moved in the deep to form the Light
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:174373:4"/> 
               <hi>Gen. 1. 2.</hi> and which the Wiſe and <hi>Pulcher ordo Mundi</hi> proceeds from. And in the Soul, he is both the Light of Nature in all, and the Light of Grace, that is, the Underſtanding in ſome, being natural in all; granted to all at their Birth by the prerogative of their Eſſence or nature above other Animals; <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightning every Man that cometh into the World. Joh. 1. 9</hi> This is what they call Reaſon: And ſupernatural in the regenerated, granted them of Grace again by the gift of the Spirit upon their Birth of Water: And this is properly that which they call Underſtanding. I ſay, he is called the word, becauſe he is Light Underſtanding and Wiſdom in us, as well as in God. <hi>Quicquid in nobis vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>det &amp; audit, verbum Dei.</hi> That Light, and that faculty whereby we ſee and perceive, and hear and underſtand things, is the Word of God in us, that is, Chriſt and his Spirit. Underſtanding comes from Chriſt, <hi>1 Joh. 5. 20.</hi> and he is the Light of Men. <hi>Joh. 1. 4, 9.</hi> and from the Spirit he ſends. <hi>Ch. 16. 17. to Guide Men into all Truth, V. 13. to teach all things. Ch. 14. 26. and to ſearch e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven the deep things of God, 1 Cor. 2. 10.</hi> underſtanding comes likewiſe. Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding is the word in the Heart. The Light whereby the Mind concei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> in the Heart, and ſends forth the Spirit thence into the Mouth, is the Wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> not the combined Syllables, nor the ſound which the Air makes in the Thr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> and in the Mouth. The Heart conceives from the Light that riſeth there the flaſh at every pullation, and ſends it into the Head, whence returning to the Heart, it is ſent with the Spirit that iſſueth out of the Flaſh into the Tongue to move it; the Tongue moving beats the Air in the Throat and in the Mouth; according to thoſe Organs which articulates its ſound, and forms the out ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken word; and ſpeaks forth the conception. So that the Light, the Spirit, and the Conceit or notion is the <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or the word: That which the vulgar call Words, being nothing but <hi>vo ces,</hi> an articulated Noiſe, and a combination of divers Sounds or Syllables, by the Spirit from the Heart; and neither the thing conceiv'd, nor the Spirit expreſſing, or ſpeaking it forth themſelves.</p>
            <p n="12">12. To conclude, Underſtanding, Reaſon and Light in the Soul is from the Spirit of Chriſt, the word of God, Chriſt himſelf; of whom we are born a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, and who worketh Faith in us. From him, and from his Spirit the hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Faith proceeds. For Underſtanding, as was ſaid before, proceeds from them, and hearing in the Scriptures ſignifyeth Underſtanding; as in that place where Chriſt ſaith, <hi>he that hath Ears to hear let him hear, &amp;c</hi> And Faith is one of the Gifts and Effects of the Spirit, <hi>1 Cor. 12. 9.</hi> No Faith without Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion, and no Converſion without Underſtanding. <hi>Matth. 13. 15.</hi> By Hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing we Believe, Turn or Convert, and what we underſtand not we neither do nor believe. <hi>Intelligere ipſum credere est,</hi> by your leave, Mr. <hi>Keith,</hi> and Madam <hi>Rome.</hi> No implicite Faith avails. When God openeth our Hearts or gives us Underſtanding, we believe as <hi>Lydia, Act. 16. 14.</hi> and confeſs with our Mouth, <hi>Rom. 10. 9. and come and ſhew our Deeds;</hi> as <hi>Zacheus, Luk. 19. 8, 9.</hi> and thoſe which burned their Learned Books, did. <hi>Act. 19. 18, 19.</hi> and Faith is dead without Deeds, <hi>Jam. 2. 26.</hi> So that to have Faith we muſt Underſtand in the firſt place, and ſo have Underſtanding; and the light of Chriſt's Spirit, or Chriſt himſelf within us. All which, if we can obtain from the outward word Preached, Mr. <hi>Keith</hi> is in the right, but then Chriſt died in vain; for he di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to get us the effect of the Promiſe, which is the Holy Spirit, <hi>Luk. 24. 49. Act. 1. 4, 5.</hi> from which Underſtanding comes.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:174373:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p n="13">13. Therefore ſince we muſt have Chriſt as a Spirit within us to Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand and Believe; we muſt know him not only without us in that Body that died upon the Croſs, to fulfil all Righteouſneſs, and reconcile us to God, <hi>Rom. 5. 10.</hi> that thereby having acceſs <hi>V. 2. Hebr. 4. 16.</hi> we might obtain his good Gift, to wit, the Holy Spirit. <hi>Matth. 7. 11. Luk. 11. 13.</hi> but within us in Spirit, ſince he cannot enter in and dwell there in Fleſh and Blood; tho' he ſhould work the Miracle of the Tranſubſtantiation; and Mr. <hi>Keith</hi> ſhould plead for an outward Chriſt, or a Chriſt without us, as hard again as he doth in his Reaſons about the 26th page. <hi>Henceforth we know Chriſt no more,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Paul. 2 Cor. 5. 16. after the Fleſh.</hi> And as a Spiritual Chriſt, form<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Kingdom of God by his Spirit <hi>Rom. 14. 17.</hi> within us. <hi>Luk. 17. 21.</hi> Eſpecially ſeeing that he is glorified again with the Glory which he had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his Incarnation. <hi>Joh. 17. 5.</hi> and ſits in that Majeſty which belongs to God alone, <hi>Hebr. 1. 3. Rev. 3. 21.</hi> and into which Fleſh and Blood cannot pretend to enter. <hi>1 Cor. 15. 50.</hi> Chriſt being to die but once. <hi>Rom. 6. 9. Hebr. 9 28.</hi> took our Fleſh and Blood once to bear our Sins in it, and now having done with it, <hi>he appears the ſecond time without Sin to Salvation,</hi> (and therefore in the Spirit; Salvation or God's Kingdom being in the Holy Ghoſt, <hi>Rom. 14. 17.) to them that look for him</hi> ſo; and are no more concerned with his Fleſh or his Body ſince he comes in the Spirit, that is, ſince his Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſion and Glorification <hi>Joh. 7. 39. Touch me not,</hi> ſaith he himſelf. <hi>Joh. 20. 17.</hi> that is, be not concerned with me whilſt in Fleſh and Blood; <hi>becauſe I am not as yet aſcended</hi> and Glorifyed, and cannot yet give you Gifts, <hi>Eph. 4. 8. viz.</hi> the Gifts of the Spirit, (of which ſee, <hi>1 Cor. 12.)</hi> or come to you in Spirit; the Holy Ghoſt being not given till after the time of his Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſion <hi>on High, Joh. 7. 39.</hi> he being not till after ready to anſwer the end of his coming in the Fleſh, to wit; to bring upon them the Promiſe of the Father, or the Gift of the Spirit; the ſhedding of which Spirit was the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filling of that ſame Promiſe as hath been ſaid, <hi>Luk. 24. 49. Act. 1. 4, 5. 2. 17, 23. Touch me not, know me no more,</hi> therefore <hi>in the Fleſh,</hi> ſaith he; for when I come to you a ſecond time to ſave you, to anſwer expectation, and the end of my coming; it ſhall not be in the Fleſh which I have died in, but in quite another form, to wit, that of a Spirit capable to comfort you, or to give you Strength and Life. <hi>Joh. 14. 18, 28.</hi> in a more Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al from than at my Reſurrection and my Transfiguration; when my groſs Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of Fleſh it ſelf <hi>Shined like the Sun. Matth. 17. 2.</hi> and paſſed through Doors and Walls. <hi>Joh. 20. 19, 26.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="14">14. And miſtake me not, Reader, I do not mean that Chriſt in puting off Fleſh and Blood, hath put off Humanity, that is the Human Nature; for then he were no more Chriſt, that is to ſay, God and Man; a Concrete of both Natures, or the Human nature Anointed with the Divine. But he remains Chriſt, or God and Man, to Eternity. For God's works are Eternal; He be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the moſt Wiſe God, whoſe Purpoſe and Power ſtands: Nothing but the Devils works (the corruption and defects introduced in the World) being to be deſtroyed. And we muſt know Chriſt, as Chriſt, or as God and Man; that is, as a thing diſtinct from God, or as a Perſon diſtinct from the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity it ſelf; to obtain Eternal Life: or elſe he had never ſaid, that <hi>it is Life Eternal to know the only true God, and Jeſus Chriſt whom he ſends. John 3. 17.</hi> Diſtinguiſhing Chriſt from God; as a Perſon ſubſiſting beſides and apart from
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:174373:5"/> God. But this, I ſay, that Chriſt hath put off his Fleſh and Blood, as being Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidental, and not at all Eſſential to Man or Humanity: For the firſt Father <hi>Adam</hi> was not Created with it, but fell in it by his Luſt; (which by Attraction drew in the Elements that took hold of him, and Tranſmuted him; made of Iſch; (a ſhining Man, ſuch as he was) an <hi>Adam;</hi> that is, a Man over-caſt with dark clouds, from <hi>Ad,</hi> a miſt) and ſo got this Monſtrous Shape. And if it were Eſſential to Man, or Human Nature, God would never deſtroy it; as he will certainly do, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6 13. to deliver the Faithful from <hi>the Body of this Death,</hi> and its reſtraint <hi>and bondage, into the glorious liberty of God's Children. Rom.</hi> 7. 24. 8. 21. 23. Man ſhall put it off himſelf, to riſe with a Spiritual, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 44. and Angelical Body. <hi>Luke</hi> 20. 36. that ſhall Shine forth as the Sun; <hi>Matth.</hi> 13. 43. as it did before the Fall, when <hi>Adam</hi> was as yet Iſch; or ſhining, from Eſch, fire. So that Chriſt as King of Men; poſſeſſing Eminently, all the Perfections to which Human Nature can pretend, hath put off that which makes Iſch <hi>Adam;</hi> a dark beaſtly man, contemptible and miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53. 3. <hi>Rom.</hi> 7. 24. And his State and Condition ought not to be ſuppoſed, ſince his Glorification, worſe than that of Man himſelf.</p>
            <p n="15">15. But to clear another Riddle; that is, how the Anointed, or the Chriſt, or Meſſiah is the ſame <hi>Quatenus</hi> God, with the Anointing Spirit, I muſt do a bold thing, which Reverend Mr. <hi>Keith</hi> will doubtleſs Bleſs himſelf at; that is, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict his Church, and <hi>Athanaſius</hi> his Creed: ſhew that <hi>Athanaſius</hi> and his Church are miſtaken; one in rendring by Perſon, the Greek word <hi>Hypoſtaſis;</hi> and <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> by Subſtance, and the other in Saying, <hi>not confounding the Perſons, nor dividing the Subſtance.</hi> For the Subſtance of the Three in the Godhead is the ſame, and is to be confounded; and their Eſſence or Nature, or their <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, ſo ought to be divided: And the word <hi>Hypoſtaſis,</hi> which they render by Perſon, doth ſignifie a Subſtance, and can bear no other Senſe; a Subſtance being that which <hi>Subſtat accidentibus:</hi> which is the very meaning and ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the word <hi>Hipoſtaſis, ab</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> &amp; <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Substo &amp; Substituor;</hi> the <hi>Hypoſtaſis</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Subjectum,</hi> or the Ground of the Three in the Godhead. And <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is Eſſence, as being the Participle of the Verb <hi>Eſſe</hi> in Greek.</p>
            <p n="16">16. Then to make Perſons in God is abſurd and impious; there being no ſuch thing as Perſons in the Godhead: for a Perſon is a thing that Subſiſteth of it ſelf, without any dependance even of that very thing it is a Relative to; as a Son can well Subſiſt altho' his Father be dead. But here in the Trinity, the Father doth not Subſiſt without the Son and Spirit; nay and is not before them: Beginning but with the Son, being but a Relative Proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to God the Son; there being in the Godhead, that is in the Unity and the ſtill Eternity, no ſuch thing as Father, and Son, and Holy Ghoſt known: all Three being, as part of the Generation of God, Included within the Bounds of this Denomination; to wit, of the Naſciture or Generation of God: the Father being not known more than the Son or Spirit, without Nature, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Generation of God, or his Manifeſtation: tho' at him this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciture or Generation Beings. <hi>Natura, quaſi dicas Naſcitura, La naiſſance,</hi> the Nativity of God, <hi>Reſpectu Creaturae,</hi> or God bringing forth himſelf to a Generation, or a Manifeſtation; to Communicate himſelf, or his good, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out himſelf to ſome things beſides himſelf. So that Nature, is only God himſelf Manifeſted; and his Motion to Nature, is his Generation. And as he moved himſelf as by three Steps or Degrees in this his Generation, he Mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſteth
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:174373:5"/> himſelf under three Appearances, Forms Natures or Eſſences, of Fire, Light and Spirit, or Father Son and Spirit; which tho' the Trinity be from Eternity in God, or Coeternal to God, that is to the Unity, the Generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of God being from Eternity, are not known, as I ſaid, before God moved himſelf to Nature without himſelf; but were hid in God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and brought to paſs in himſelf before his outward Nature, or his manifeſtation; the Godhead in Unity, as it is without Nature, being but a dark Abyſs. And theſe three appearances or diſtinct forms and degrees of Gods manifeſtation, are called Father, and Son, and Spirit: Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, becauſe the Godhead or Unity is the ground, the ſtock, the Womb that brings forth out of its deep the Light, its firſt Born or Son, and only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten Son; called Son by the Hebrews, on the very ſame account as their Language calls a Spark, <hi>the Son of the burning Coal:</hi> Son, becauſe he doth come forth like a Spark out of the Coal, by breaking and ſhining forth out of the dark lump or deep, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 6. And thirdly, they are called by the name of the Spirit, becauſe the ſame Unity doth not only ſhew it ſelf, or make it ſelf manifeſt in the Light, or by the Son; but makes it ſelf to be felt, and communicates its good in the form of a Spirit, or Beams flowing from the Light; nothing in Nature being ſo fit to diffuſe convey and communicate the good as the Light and its efflux; the Influences whereof are the Holy Ghoſt in God; and in the World, the Spirit which makes what we call the Air, by vapou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſing Water, or turning it to vapour.</p>
            <p n="17">17. <hi>Quaere.</hi> What is a Spirit? <hi>Anſwer.</hi> It is a Subſtance as imperceptible as God himſelf to natural Men, whoſe knowledge goeth no higher than ſenſe and intelligece 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. 14. The thing that is, and exiſts, <hi>Exod.</hi> 3. 14. (for it is the ſame as God, who is but a pure Spirit. <hi>Joh.</hi> 4. 24.) the ſubſtance of ſubſtances that actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ates all ſubſtance, and gives it form and Eſſence. In God alone, and the Soul (to wit, regenerated) it is ſimple, immaterial, but in this World, where it was at firſt mixt with the Water, its concrete and material, and hath the three dimenſions that all other concretes have, and is that which raiſeth up the Water into vapours. Out of it and of Water comes all ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial Subſtance or Matter; for out of both, this material World was made, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. 2. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. 5. All things, ſaith <hi>Lucretius,</hi> are come from their ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual and their inviſible State, to a viſibility and a palpability. By its joyning to Water, which it inſpiſſates to Oyl, then concocts into a Salt, Earth and Body comes to be: Corporification and Terrification, being one and the ſame thing. And by its ſeparation and freedom from its vehicle, whilſt it is clearing it ſelf of the Vapour that holds it; (for it leaves it not wholly; not a ſpark of pure Spirit being ſuffered in the World, for then it would inflame it) fire and the deſtruction of things compacted by it, (for <hi>ejus ope totum cum toto compactum eſt)</hi> are ſtill made and come to paſs. From the Spirit all encreaſe, and decreaſe or corruption of material things, proceed. From the Spirit as Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, their Multiplication; Multiplication being but a flux or extenſion of the firſt central Spirit infuſed into the deep, and a propagation made <hi>a traduce</hi> of the ſame: and from it as a fire, <hi>Quateuus</hi> become fire, their decreaſe and corruption, that is, the ſeparation of that which was compacted. In fine, the ſtock of all things, of God and of the Creature, being Spirit, and all things coming from a ſpiritual inviſible and unknown ſtate into materiality, Ken, perceptibility, all things agree in ſubſtance; and as God is a Spirit,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:174373:6"/> and Spirit is the ſubſtance and ſtock of the Deity, the three in the Deity, which we call the Trinity, agree into this one thing, and are but one in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, not ſo in Form or Eſſence.</p>
            <p n="18">18. And the Truth is, the Scripture ſpeaking of Perſons no where, there is no reaſon wherefore we ſhould ſet up this Notion, and make of Hypoſtaſis, (which is the ſtock and ſubſtance) the things dependent of it, <hi>viz.</hi> the form or the Perſons; tho' I am not ignorant that the Schools make of the form what I make of ſubſtance, to wit, The moſt Eſſential and Principal part of things. But Chriſtians who learn of Chriſt, being anointed by him with that which <hi>teacheth all things. Joh.</hi> 14. 26. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2. 27. or elſe they were not Chriſtians; for a Chriſtian ſignifyeth one that is anointed; ought not to take upon tick from the Schools and the Heathen, their Theoſophick Notions; nor ſuch as is or may be the occaſion of Errours; but from Nature and Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, and the Etymology of words if they have any; as here of Hypoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis <hi>ab</hi> &amp; <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; which is by no Greek Author made uſe of to ſignify an individual Perſon. And the Scriptures ſpeak only <hi>of Three,</hi> or a Trinity, <hi>which bear Record</hi> in the World, or make known the Deity; which three things agree in one, and are One and the ſame Thing. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5. 7. in the ſtock or the ſubſtance, but divers in the Eſſence. The Nature or the Eſſence of the Light being divers from that of the dark fire, which is the Father of it; and from that of the Spirit, or beams that flow out of both; as is that of the Spirit different from that of both the Light and Fire likewiſe.</p>
            <p n="19">19. And that it is ſo, to wit, that theſe three appearances being divers in Eſſence, are the ſame in the ſubſtance, or one and the ſame Spirit; and ſo, that the Holy Ghoſt and Chriſt, as the Light of God, and the ſecond Appearance of the Three in the Godhead, are but One and the ſame Thing, St. <hi>John</hi> ſaith, there be three things in Earth bear Record of it, the Spirit, Water and Blood; which laſt, is but a concrete of Water and of Spirit, digeſted and concocted in the Animal Bodies: and I ſay, that all things in the whole World witneſs it; the World it ſelf, Man and Beaſt, Minerals and Vegetables. All things being more or leſs, <hi>Secundum modum ſuum,</hi> after the Image of God; God being every where <hi>ſemper ſibi ſimilis;</hi> and manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf in all things, ſuch as he is, in Trinity like himſelf.</p>
            <p n="20">20. Firſt, in the whole World it ſelf, where God is made manifeſt by Fire Light and Spirit; We ſee firſt an influence from the Sun and from the Stars, into ſublunary things, and a refluence from them back a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain into the Sun and the Stars, to ſupply them and feed their Fire and Flame. Any Man that hath but ſenſe, and warms himſelf in the Sun, and will hold his hand over a burning ſtick or Candle may feel this Flux and Reflux. This influence in the Sun, in the Air, and in the Flame of the ſtick, is a Spirit, moving always from the Sun into the Air and all things, and from them to any Flame; and chiefly towards the Sun which is the great Sea of Flames, and as having need of more ſupply attracts moſt of it. There, in the Orbe of the Sun, or in the ſpace of the Flame where it meets and concentreth, it forms the Fire and Light; and flowing out of that ſpace into the Air, (whence it came) in the form of Beams and Smoak, (which makes the ſpots of the Sun) it returns to a Spirit; and by this Circulation makes the Gold Chain of <hi>Homer,</hi> that tyeth the Earth to Heaven, and keeps the Earth from falling to
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:174373:6"/> pieces, as Poets ſay. Now, this ſpirit is the ſame in the Air or in the Deep; in the Flame or in the Sun; as out of the Sun and Flame; whilſt it flows towards the flame, as whilſt it is in the flame, and when it comes out of it: on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly varying it ſelf into the ſeveral forms of fire, light and ſpirit; and putting on divers ſhapes. But theſe things being too high, or however too crabbed for common Capacities, and for thoſe <hi>Vertuoſi Prov.</hi> 24. 7. who feed upon fool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſhneſs, <hi>Chap.</hi> 15. 14. I will bring them in here by way of Annotation, <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <p>
                     <hi>We may learn from the Scriptures, if we cannot ſee Nature, that there was a dark Abyſs, and in the Center of it the Spirit of God working, and moving it ſelf upwards towards the Circumference.</hi> Gen. 1. 2. <hi>and not upon the Surface, as the Modern tranſlate it. For God produced the World and all things out of Himſelf, and therefore is the Center of all things; from which all things flow to the Circumference. Now, when this Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit had thus moved it ſelf for a while, or the ſpace of the firſt Night (which we ſuppoſe of 12 Hours, for the World was created about the firſt Equinoxe) and had met and gathered in ſufficient quantity to ſupply the ſpace of it, about the bounds and Limits which God hath ſet to this World, ſtopping there, it concentred; and by this Concen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tration, which was the Word,</hi> fiat Lux; <hi>(for God's Word is His Power, Act and Will, as I ſaid) it broke out into a Light, or ſhined out of Darkneſs,</hi> 2 Cor. 4. 6. <hi>as the Lightning doth yet now out of the thick and dark Clouds, and became the Light it ſelf. But before it concentred, whilſt it was yet in Motion, or moving, it was Fire. The Fire being nothing but the Spirit in Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and moving towards its end, which is the ſame as the End of Nature, to wit, The Light, or the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtation: The Light being,</hi> ſaith <hi>St. Paul,</hi> Eph. 5. 13. <hi>the only Thing manifeſt,</hi> that is to ſay, <hi>the ſame thing as God's Manifeſtation. (St.</hi> Paul'<hi>s Words are;</hi> All that is manifeſt is Light, <hi>and not all that which</hi> makes <hi>manifeſt, as they do miſconſtrue it) the only diffuſive Thing, and fit to communicate, or to manifeſt the Good. And we never ſee any Heat or Fire produced but by Motion of Spirits; as by filing in Iron, rubbing in Wood</hi> (viz. <hi>two Sticks of Wood together) fermentation in Liquors in moiſt Herbs, and in wet Hay. From Fire, when it attains the Light and the liberty (after flying</hi> confertim, <hi>and meeting and gathering together into ſome ſpace) it turns to a Blaze or Flame; when it hath diſſipated the Darkneſs, or dark Vehicle of Smoak which it raiſeth with; and brought both Extreams, that is, both it ſelf and the Water, to a Harmonious Temper; For it is the Harmony and Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical mixture of the two great Contraries, to wit: Fire and Water, that by the Concentration of one, and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſipation of the other, form the Light.</hi> Amicitia con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariorum &amp; diſſimilium commixtio Lumen conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuunt, illuſtratum ab actu Dei; <hi>That is by his Word, which concentred in a point the Spirit that aſcended. That the Light is produced by Concentration appears from ſmall Eyes which ſee better than full and promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent ones: And from the burning Glaſſes that make it by concentring again the diffuſed Beams, and reflecting them upon ſome Combuſtible Matter, whoſe Moiſture is not ſo much bound up as is that in Metals; and ſo lays more expoſed to the Action of thoſe Beams, than that in the burning Glaſs. And by the just Proportion of Fire and of Water, appears, from that no Fire can burn or produce a Flame, when no Air, which is full of moiſt Vapours, can come to it; or where the Moiſture abounds, and the Spirit is not able to diſſipate the Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pour, and to dry up the Moiſture. This ſame Spirit, I ſay, having obtained its end, (the Light, and the Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty from the Bounds of the Vapour which it had elevated) and continuing its Courſe or Motion out of the ſpace, where the Flame or the Light ſhines, turns again to a Spirit, flows out in the Form of Beams, which any Body may feel; and by expanding again</hi> in ampliorem Autam <hi>then the ſpace the Flame was in, becomes again inviſible: but, as conveying with it the Impreſſion of the Light, of a more beneficent and vivifying Nature than at firſt when it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowed, and moved towards the Sun. And thoſe Beams are but the ſame in Subſtance as the Light is; or as it was in the light, and when it moved to it: being the ſame in Subſtance, not in Form and Conſiſtence, in the</hi> Light <hi>as out of it; the Subſtance being not new, nor changed from what it was centrally, or in it ſelf; but putting on divers Shapes, or the three Faces of three ſeveral Phoenomenons; or appearing in the Form of Fire, Light and Spirit; all three different from that of the Spirit in the deep, conſider'd as not moving, or as yet in the Center of the Deep; or as in God in the ſtill Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, before he moved himſelf: and diſtinct from each other: The Light, as I have ſaid, being of a gentle, meek, comforting, and refreſhing, and vivifying Nature; whereas that of the Spirit (whilſt it moves towards the light, and is deprived of it) is to be a dark Fire, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuming and cauſing Wo; cold and ſharp, auſtere and fierce, like that of a corroding bitter Froſt in a dark Night; of</hi> Lapis infernalis, <hi>the Gangrene,</hi> Aqua for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis, <hi>and of</hi> Ignis Gehennae, <hi>that gnaws, corrodes, ſtings and ſhutes, like the Worm that never dies, and a ſore Boil not yet ripe, and makes one die Raving mad. The Fire of Hell is cold and burning without ſhining; as appears from that Chriſt ſaith, it cauſeth gnaſhing of Teeth, and is in outer Darkneſs.</hi> Matth. 8. 12.</p>
                  <p n="21">21. <hi>Next in the little World, Man.</hi> Reſpice, <hi>ſaith</hi> Triſmegiſte, <hi>when thou wilt conceive ſomething of God as Father of all,</hi> Quid tibi accidat generare vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenti. <hi>Firſt, when a Man is in Love, he becomes pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive and dark, from his Luſt that obſcures him; for Luſt being attractive and binding; (the aſtringent or attractive quality coming only from the Lust or the longing in nature, as may be ſeen in</hi> Acids, <hi>which coagulate, becauſe they are of an eſurine or deſirous quality, whence Corporification or Terrification comes; and whence the Earth, as having moſt of this bodyfying or aſtringent quality, draws the needle in the Compaſs, and by attracting of it, cauſeth its variation Eaſtward in the Northern Seas, as being there, on that ſide, larger than towards the Weſt; and Weſtward, beyond the Line, upon the Coaſt of</hi> Brazil; <hi>the Earth being larger there on that ſide, than in</hi> Africk.) <hi>I ſay, that Luſt being astringent or attractive, draws or attracts to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and condenſeth in the Mind the Spiritual Idea of the Thing luſted after, and fills up the Mind with it, which becomes adumbrated or darkned as the Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhine by the interpoſition of that which caſts a ſhadow: at the ſame time, the Spirits moving in the darkned deep towards the Parts and Organs proper to Generation, kindle and make in that party the Dark ſtate of the Father of the Light, and gathering in ſufficient quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity, break out by concentration, when the Parts can hold no more, and can hold out no longer, into a Light, Flaſh or Flame;</hi> fit Lux: <hi>The Son or the Seed comes forth with Delight and Joy, a ſign that the Son is Born. The</hi> Pulchrum <hi>and the</hi> Bonum, <hi>to be good and delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, being the Nature Eſſence and Property of the Light. The Pleaſure in begetting is a relick of the Light, and the Good of Paradiſe. Col. 1. 12. Then this ſame Son, Flaſh or Seed, turning to Spirit again, becomes a thin Breath or Steam, that ſteams from that place or part which the Flaſh did break out in, into that Cell of the Womb where the Conception is made; leav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing behind it the Sperm or the groſs part of the Seed; for it comes out afterwards, which is a demonſtration it went not in with the ſteam; for that Cell ſhuts cloſe upon't, and doth not open again till the time of bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forth. In the Womb that ſame ſteam is, by the binding quality of the Spirit of the Male, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agulated like Cheeſe,</hi> Job. 10. 20. <hi>and becomes the Fruit or Son, tho' it was the Son before, as ſoon as the Fleſh appear'd: For it is the Son as ſoon as it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes Prolifick, not becauſe 'tis in the Womb, the Womb receiving it not, and yielding no Fruit or Son, except it be ſuch before it ſteams or comes into it: And it becomes Prolifick in the Falſh when both the Male and Female Flaſh together, and when the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of both Joyn and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nite in the Flaſh: So that it becomes the Son from that very place in Man where the Flaſh or Light is made, whilst it is yet in the Man. (Note, that the Male and Female in that act make but one Man) before it gets in the Womb. All the while this laſt Spirit which gives life unto the Son, and is become his Spirit, being the ſame as moved in the Deep of the Parents, and brake out into a Flaſh, and in the form of a ſteam got in the Cell of the Womb. The ſame, whilſt in the Father, moving to Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, as whilſt flaſhing, ſteaming out, and getting into the Womb; and at, whilſt animating, and vivifying the Son. Thus remaining Father Son and Spirit at the ſame time, and always the ſame Spirit in ſubſtance, and the ſame thing, tho' paſſing through three divers Steps Degrees and Forms or States.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Man being not wholly made and formed out of this World, but partly from above it, hath an Image of God more than all other worldly things, to wit, the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding and the Will, and the Courage or Power to act and do: which three are actuated, rectifyed and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by one and the ſame Spirit, to wit; by the Comforter or the Power from on High, that giveth <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding and Strength to know and act by, enlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and directing thoſe three Faculties in Man: The <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderstanding to Know, the Will to Chuſe or refuſe, and the Power to perform and reduce into Practice that thing, the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding knows and diſcerns to be good, and the Will chuſeth for ſuch. As the Faculties in Man, ſo in God the Attributes, not only the Trinity, but his Omnipotency and All-ſufficiency, Eternity,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>come from one Central Spirit, and the ſame Might and Power, exerting it ſelf like Beams, reflected ſeveral ways.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And laſtly, in Plants, and Stones, Minerals and Vegetables, we may obſerve the ſame thing. Firſt a Potential Fire and Might mixed with Water, whence their Body comes to be: for both Stones and Minerals yield this fire by striking, and Plants by fermentation: which Might, Fire or Spirit produceth in that Body a Sap, a Marrow or Oyl which is their Light and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue; the Chymiſts call it Eſſence, and thoſe Oyls Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſential Oyls: And thirdly they yield a Smell and Taſte, which is the Spirit reſulting from the two first, and by which they Spring, and grow and yield their Fruit or Vertue, which laſt, is not different from the firſt, that gives them life, and forms their Sap and Body. It appears from rotten Apples which ſmell ſtrongeſt when they are a rotting or corrupting, and from Sweet ſmelling Flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, that yield no Eſſential Oyl when they have lost their Odour; that this ſmell is their Virtue, and the ſame as gave them life, and made them to grow and Spring, ſince they decay and periſh as ſoon as they have loſt it. When you hold your hand over the Flame of a Stick or Candle, you feel the Beams or Spirit coming from the Flame or Light, which came firſt into the Flame from the dark lump of the ſtick, or of the Fat or Tallow, and gave the Stick or Tallow both its body and its life; and ſo is the very ſame in the Stick and in the Flame, as you feel warming your hand, going from the light or flame into the Air, whence it came, into the Sap of the Tree, and into the ſtick and Flame, making a Flux and Reflux of one and the ſame Spirit, from all things into the Air, and the Sun, and other Flames, and from the Sun back again into the Air, and all things upon Earth, to give them life, and ſo an Eternal Chain, a perpetual Motion, and Circulation of life.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> for the Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſort of People: and go on with the main Point in Hand, concluding from thence that; as we ſee in the World, and in all other Beings, the fire light and ſpirit to be the ſame in ſubſtance, and one and the ſame ſpirit: ſo it is in God likewiſe, but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minently, that is, in a more ſublime manner, as (for Illuſtration ſake) is felt in the Peace and Joy, and burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Conſcience, when after a long conflict of grief, horror and deſpair (called the fiery Tryal, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4. 12.) Light breaks out in the dark Soul, and it hath Light and gladneſs. <hi>Eſth.</hi> 8. 16. God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a pure Spirit, free from Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and all that the Spirit is ſubject to both in Man and in the World: (where being mixt with Water (for there is not an Atome of it unmixt in the World, or it would ſoon en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flame it, and reduce it to Aſhes) it becomes Corporeal, and hath the three Dimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:174373:7"/> except in the Soul of Man, which is not all of this World) and not only a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, but the ſpirit of Spirits, that actuates all Spirits, and is their Form and their Soul; doth act moſt tranſcendently, and is not confined to the ſame Laws, Order and Rules, as created Spirits are in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagating themſelves. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do I ſuppoſe that the heat of the fire was manifeſted in God, as it is now in the Sun; for God, as God, is the Good, meer Love, Light, Joy, and Delight, inwhom there is no darkneſs, fierceneſs or auſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 1. 5. 4. 16. and in him therefore is no fire and heat perceptible anger and auſterity; but in the Creature only, when it departs from the Light and the Love of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe. But the Scripture teaching us that God is an angry God, and a conſuming fire; we may believe that in God is the root of the fire, ſerving as the Gall in Man, and Acids in ſweet Liquors, to exacuate the Light and Love of his bleſſed State; Love and Light being the State in which God aquieſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth. <hi>Matth.</hi> 13. 17. Being not properly God in the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and Spirit, but in the Light of the Son, in whom he is well pleaſed. And <hi>St. John</hi> ſaith, that the World (being the Image of God, as well as Man and his Soul) repreſents the Trinity; or <hi>bears witneſs</hi> by three things, which all Men may ſee there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, in one and the ſame ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject (to wit: in the firſt Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:174373:7"/> infuſed into the Deep) of the Trinity in God: for he ſaith they bear witneſs to the Father, to the Word, and to the Holy Spirit, which is the whole Trinity; and <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, that by the World and the Things which are therein, we may not only find out, but <hi>clearly ſee</hi> the God-head. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. 20. that is, God in Unity in the ſtill Eternity, and all the deep things of God, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. 10. ſuch as is the Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. And I believe we may, for I ſee it my ſelf.</p>
            <p n="21">21. And I ſee through the World, not only the Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, but the Coeternity of the three Appearances: that, as no Light can exiſt and ſubſiſt without Fire, and nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther without the Air: So in God there is no Son, nor Father without Spirit, nor no Spirit without Light, but all three appear at once, from the very beginning of God's Manifeſtation. <hi>Joh.</hi> 1. 2. And I ſee there likewiſe the Generation of God; God generating himſelf, and being generated, and introducing himſelf by his Beams and his Efflux, at firſt into the Great World, next into the little World, and thirdly, (when both were fall'n, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prav'd and corrupted) into the Seed of a Maid; there to ſupply the Office of the Spirit in Mans Seed, and to beget the Man God, Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, the Redeemer of all things from Corruption, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 21, 23. And fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and laſtly, by the Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or the Mean of that
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:174373:8"/> Man God, into the Soul of all thoſe that look for him in Spirit, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 9. 28. and know him ſpiritually, 1 <hi>Cor. 2. 24. 11. 29. Secundum modum tamen recipientis</hi> in each, that is, as every one doth evacuate himſelf, or ſet himſelf in order, or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare himſelf for it. <hi>Act.</hi> 13. 48. But moſt ſuperlatively in his third introduction; his Efflux, the Holy Ghoſt which Chriſt was Conceived by, bringing with him at that time all the might of the Father, and the virtue of the Light; <hi>the fulneſs of the Godhead dwelling in Chriſt bodily,</hi> Col. 2. 9. he having not received the Holy Ghoſt by Meaſure. <hi>Joh.</hi> 3. 34. And if thou hadſt my Spectacles, which I cannot lend thee, (Science is the Gift of God, not of Man, nor of the Schools) thou wouldſt ſee and believe it alſo as well as I, without the help of Scripture; for thou wouldſt underſtand it, and to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, is to believe, <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligere, ipſum credere eſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="22">22. And thou wouldſt ſee and believe therefore that the Son of Man, as the Son and Light of God, is the ſame as Gods Spirit, and comes with the Holy Ghoſt, bringing with him in his Wings, or the Efflux of his Light, Health and Life, or Salvation, <hi>Mal.</hi> 4. 2. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſame in ſubſtance: and being not a Perſon or ſubject diſtinct from them. But that as the Son of Man or <hi>Emmanuel,</hi> God in Man, or as the Human Nature a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:174373:8"/> with the Divine; he is as much a Perſon ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting a part from God, tho' in an undivided manner) as the Church from him, and as the Beams from the Sun) as Man and the World it ſelf. And thou wouldſt ſee how he is the <hi>Firſt Born</hi> of the Creature, or <hi>of the whole Creation.</hi> Col. 1. 15. (not of <hi>every</hi> Creature, for that Tranſlation is falſe) the <hi>only begotten Son of</hi> God, and dwelling in God the Father, and God in him: <hi>Joh.</hi> 1. 1. 14. 11. and how he is one with God. <hi>Ch.</hi> 10. 30. and not only one with him, but the moſt Bright Glorious and Excellent of the three Eſſences of the Godhead; (the Light or Oyl of gladneſs which he is anointed with <hi>Ch. 1. 9, 14. Hebr.</hi> 1. 9.) And yet leſs than the Father, who <hi>Quatenus</hi> the Godhead <hi>is greater</hi> than the Perſon of Chriſt, or of God and Man. <hi>Joh.</hi> 14. 28. In fine, how as God and Man, he becomes the Son of Man; not only of one Virgin, but of all the Virgin Souls that will make themſelves Virgins, or diſ-impregnate themſelves of the Luſts and Affections they are fill'd with from their Youth, <hi>Matth.</hi> 24. 19. till Chriſt is form'd in them. <hi>Gal.</hi> 4. 19. that is, before their new Birth of Water and of Spirit: And the Head, and the Spring Head, and the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of Mankind. <hi>Eph.</hi> 1. 22. <hi>Col.</hi> 1. 18. (inſtead of the firſt <hi>Adam,)</hi> where all the Sons of <hi>Adam</hi> muſt re-enter and die in, become as dead as Water. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6. 4. and as one Water with him, that they may be born again of him and of his Spirit, and as the Brooks of the Spring, become partakers of his Nature, and his Righteouſneſs. And as ſuch, that is, <hi>as Head over all things to the Church,</hi> Eph. 1. 22. he deſerves, tho' but a Man, or however God and Man; that every Knee of Things both in Heaven and in Earth ſhould bow and fall at his Name. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2. 10.</p>
            <p n="23">23. I thought fit to enlarge upon this Particular; (1.) Becauſe it is the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of many Controverſies, eaſily reconcilable, if Men made uſe of Reaſon, or of the Light of Nature in ſtudying Divinity, and reading of the Scriptures; and did not make the Scriptures to ſpeak as their Opinion; I mean, did not rather endeavour to make Scripture ſay the ſame thing as they ſay, than ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine what they ſay by that which the Scriptures ſay; yet no better com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed than by procuring an Act of Parliament againſt thoſe which they call the <hi>Socinians.</hi> (2.) <hi>Secondly,</hi> becauſe Mankind is grown ſo blind and ſupine in Matters of Religion, that not only the Scripture, and the Thing it containeth, ſpecified by Mr. <hi>Keith,</hi> pag. 10. of his <hi>Sermon,</hi> are to him a meer Parable, which he neither underſtands, <hi>Mark</hi> 4. 11. nor endeavours to do it; having got this ſtrange Notion, that they are too high for him; that <hi>St. Paul</hi> is miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken, and Mr. <hi>Keith</hi> in the right: <hi>St. Paul</hi> in ſaying, that the inviſible things
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:174373:9"/> of God may be known and underſtood by the works of Creation, and even without Scripture, for he ſpeaks of the Heathen, who have it not to peruſe; and <hi>ſo clearly</hi> too, adds he, that they are without Excuſe, who do not know God thereby. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. 20. and Mr. <hi>Keith,</hi> in ſaying, that all thoſe things can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be underſtood but by Scripture; and that they conſider God as a great way from His works; whereas he is their Virtue and Spirit of Life Himſelf; and that ſame <hi>Word of Power</hi> within them, that <hi>upholds them. Heb. 1. 3. (3.) Thirdly,</hi> becauſe many Books of Mr. <hi>Keith</hi> and others (to which this is an Anſwer) tend more than ever before towards the eſtabliſhing of a ſufficiency of Scripture Revelation, and an implicite knowledge of God by the outward Word, and a School Divinity; and to null the Light within, that is, the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Teachings of God's Spirit in the Soul; and God's Knowledge by Nature. Whereas Men are by <hi>St. Paul,</hi> Rom. 1. 20. and the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> 5. 12. blamed for not regarding the Works of God in Nature; the Knowledge of God by it being more plain and eaſy. <hi>Prov.</hi> 14. 6. than his knowledge by Scripture; Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture being Properly God himſelf manifeſted. Natural Philoſophy is Divinity it ſelf: which hath ceaſed amongſt Men, ſince the <hi>Schools</hi> and the <hi>Schoolmen,</hi> leaving Nature and Scripture, have taught it by ſo many Diſtinctions, Defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and other <hi>Oppoſitions and vain</hi> Terms of their <hi>Science, falſly ſo call'd,</hi> ſaith <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 Tim. 6. 20. that Men being confounded, know not what to make of them, nor how to learn by their Means. <hi>Non est in intellectu quod non fuit in Senſu,</hi> is one of their own Notions; yet they will teach to know God by cramp Words and <hi>vain Bablings,</hi> without the Light of Nature. Since Printing, Men, leaving off the uſe of their own Reaſon, think to <hi>ſteal from</hi> other Men the Word and Knowledge of God. <hi>Jer.</hi> 23. 30. and their <hi>Study</hi> being now to ſet up vaſt Libraries to look upon and read in; it is no wonder if they miſſing the Reaſons of Things, gather from Reading only Scraps of other Mens Notions; and fill their Heads with a Heap of in-coherent Why mſies, from which they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not deduce a Natural Conſequence, and ſo build on wild Conceits, a new Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion, and a new Philoſophy, which hath no ground in Nature. (4.) <hi>And laſtly,</hi> becauſe the End and Deſign of this Paper is not ſo much to refute, or to deſtroy and pull down the Building of Mr. <hi>Keith,</hi> as to build up in its room ſuch work as may abide. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. 14. all things being to be done for Edification, and the good of the Neighbour. <hi>Rom.</hi> 15. 2.</p>
            <p n="24">24. And to conclude my Anſwer and Remarks on the Miſtakes of Mr. <hi>Keith</hi> in this Point, to wit: of the Means of Faith and of Regeneration, by what means they are wrought and brought to paſs in the Soul; I ſay, if Faith be one of the Operations, Gifts and Effects of God's Spirit, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> teacheth it is, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. 9. it follows, that it is not wrought by the outward Word, but by the Spirit Himſelf; and that the Word and Spirit being both Agents of it, may be thought one and the ſame. Faith comes by Underſtanding. <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. 17. and Underſtanding comes from the Inſpiration of God, or his Spirit within us. <hi>Job</hi> 32. 8. that guides us into all Truth. <hi>Job.</hi> 16. 13. Therefore Faith is effected by the Light of that Spirit opening the Heart, and the Eyes, as to <hi>Lydia.</hi> Acts 16. 14. and <hi>Agar. Gen.</hi> 21. 19. the three Wiſemen of the Eaſt, <hi>Matth. 2. 2. Cornelius</hi> and others, Act. 10. 44. to underſtand and believe, and not by the outward Word. <hi>Before time in Iſrael, the Prophets</hi> that is to ſay, knew Him <hi>were called Seers, 1 Sam.</hi> 9. 9. becauſe they ſaw God, that is to ſay, knew Him by His works. 1 <hi>Kings.</hi> 17. 1. But now the Caſe is altered, according to
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:174373:9"/> Mr. <hi>Keith,</hi> and that for the worſe beſides, againſt what he ſaith himſelf of a better Covenant to Believers, <hi>pag.</hi> 9. and the many Promiſes of God's Spirit to Chriſtians, who are now but bare Hearers, and that not of God Himſelf; but of Men and of their Word. If Faith be wrought in Man but <hi>by the Doctrine of Christ, as it is preached to him;</hi> the Faith of them that believe that which Mr. <hi>Keith</hi> preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth is erroneous and falſe, as by what I have ſhew'd, it doth already appear.</p>
            <p n="25">25. Mr. <hi>Keith</hi> having thus ſaid, that it is the outward Word which begets the Saints again, and that worketh Faith in them, concludes in the 9th <hi>Page,</hi> that <hi>the written Word therefore</hi> is not only the <hi>compleat and the adequate Rule of our Faith and Practice, but that the Precepts thereof are of far larger extent than thoſe writ in Man's heart, without, or before man hath the Scripture Revelation:</hi> prov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it by a Paſſage which maketh nothing for him. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. 96. <hi>David's</hi> meaning in that Place, being not of the outward or written Word of God; for the Law and the Prophets, which make up the written Word, were not extant in his time; there being not yet extant more than the Books of <hi>Joſhua, Judges,</hi> and the <hi>Pentateuch:</hi> but of the Law written in his Heart, and of that word, which he kept hid <hi>in his Heart, v</hi> 11. and which he deſireth God by no means to hide from him, <hi>v.</hi> 19. but to enlarge or open his heart wide <hi>V.</hi> 32. to contain it. <hi>V.</hi> 18. 33, 34.</p>
            <p n="26">26. To which my Anſwer is, firſt, that the Spirit which writes the Law, and Precepts of God in the Heart of Believers, <hi>teacheth and ſearcheth all things, even the deep things of God,</hi> not revealed in Scripture, <hi>Joh.</hi> 14. 26. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. 10. <hi>And guideth into all Truth. Joh.</hi> 16. 13. Therefore the Law written by it in the Heart of Men, is of a larger extent than all that the Written or Preached Word can ſuggeſt. Secondly, that <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith, 2 <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 1. 19. that the <hi>Word of Prophecy,</hi> or the Law and the Prophets (which was all the writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten word was extant in <hi>Peters</hi> time) is but <hi>untill the day dawn, and the Day or Morning Star,</hi> (which is Chriſt the inward word, <hi>Ap.</hi> 22. 16.) ariſe and ſhine in the Heart. It is no more at thy word, as ſome ſaid to their Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, the <hi>Samaritain</hi> Woman. <hi>Joh.</hi> 4. 42. that we have Faith or Believe; but becauſe we our ſelves have heard Chriſt, and know from him that he is really the Chriſt, and the Saviour of the World. Which ſhews that the inward word goeth beyond all the Scriptures and Scripture Revelation. And thirdly, that Chriſt himſelf by theſe words; <hi>I have yet many things to ſay to you, which you cannot as yet bear</hi> before the Holy Ghoſt comes; <hi>but when he comes to guide you into the Truth of all things, he will ſuggeſt them to you;</hi> nay, <hi>and ſhew you things to come.</hi> Joh. 16. 12, 13. (which laſt things, <hi>viz.</hi> things to come, the Scripture declares no where but Enigmatically, as in the Revelations) ſhews us, ſince he had as yet many things to ſay to us, and doth refer us for them to the Light and the guidance of God's Spirit, when he comes, that all that he had to ſay is not contain'd in Scripture, and that the Light comes from it, is not ſo great and ſo full as that of the Inward Word. And ſince what he had to ſay, is as Neceſſary to Life as what he had ſaid except we ſuppoſe and grant that he might ſpeak idle words, that ſha'nt ſtand but paſs away, <hi>Matth.</hi> 24. 35. and hath condemned himſelf. <hi>Ch.</hi> 12. 36. the Scripture doth not contain all that is neceſſary for life, and for Salvation; and ſo is not the compleat rule of Faith, and of Practice. St. <hi>Paul</hi> to ſhew that he did not take the word he preach'd for the compleat rule of Faith, nor for a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Revelation of the things to be known and believed, refers thoſe he
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:174373:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> preached to for the Truth of what he preach'd, to the Revelation of God by the word in them. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2. 15. as being that which God ſpeaks to the Saints by ſince Chriſt's time. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 1. 2. St. <hi>John</hi> alſo by ſaying <hi>that the World would not contain the Books might be written of all that Christ did.</hi> Ch. 21. 25. <hi>and Taught</hi> Act. 1. 1. ſhews that the written Word doth not contain all the Laws and Doctrine and Works of Chriſt, which he did for an example. 1 <hi>Cor. 11. 1. Pet.</hi> 2. 21. that its Laws are not ſo full as thoſe writ in the Mind and Heart by the Inward Word; and that it is not therefore the compleat Rule of Conſcience.</p>
            <p n="27">27. Mr. <hi>Keith</hi> in his Wiſdom, being conſcious of this Truth (for he had formerly taught Immediat. Revel. pag. 96. that <hi>he that ſeeks for the Light in the writtin outward Word and for Life,</hi> or to get Life, or be Born again by it, <hi>ſeeks the living among the dead; the Light being not therein but in Chriſt,</hi> the Inward Word) adds to this Doctrine of his, pag. 9. and 11. <hi>that the Knowledge and the Faith of the Myſteries and things revealed in the Scriptures,</hi> (which he relates pag. 10.) <hi>are given us by the Word Preach'd and heard outwardly, with the illumination and working of the Spirit,</hi> or Word <hi>of God inwardly: And would not have any think</hi> (Retract. p. 12.) that he relinquiſheth God's inward Revelation, and teachings by his Spirit. Joyning here both the inward and outward word together, as neceſſary for Faith and the right underſtanding of the Scriptures, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but aſcribing Faith before wholly to the outward Word. Thus affirming in one place that which he will not confeſs, but denies in the other, and confounding both at laſt, I mean both the inward and outward Word, to confound and ſurprize the unwary; and to leave ſome holes open for himſelf to evade at. For if both neceſſary for underſtanding and Faith, why doth he lay ſuch ſtreſs upon the outward elſwhere, ſaying it is the compleat and adequate Rule of Faith? And what hath this Learned Man diſputed for all the while?</p>
            <p n="28">28. The Truth is, that both theſe words do very well together, being the two witneſſes that do teſtify of Chriſt. <hi>Joh.</hi> 5. 39. 15. 26, 27. and in the Mouth of which two, every word which we read in the one is confirmed, <hi>Ch.</hi> 8. 17. But the outward word alone is far from being capable of guiding into the Truth of what it ſaith or relates, of convincing, and being the full rule of the Conſcience. Being but like a Parable, or dark to natural Men. <hi>Mark 4. 11. 1 Cor.</hi> 2. 14. who (witneſs all the errors of ſo many Chriſtian Sects) cannot find the Truth by it: and imperfect of it ſelf, teaching no where (for inſtance) what are the fiery Tryal, and thoſe Sufferings of Chriſt, St. <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> makes mention of, 1 <hi>Ep.</hi> 4. 12. and how God hath brought himſelf into Nature, and into Man and the World: What death <hi>Adam</hi> died of on the day he Tranſgreſſed. <hi>Gen.</hi> 2. 17. what was the Sin of Angels, and many other ſuch things. Beſides, as I have ſhew'd by ſeveral inſtances, it is not well tranſlated, nor divided in Verſes, making two Verſes of one; as of the 15. and 16. of the 2d of <hi>Romans,</hi> which ought to be but one Verſe. And o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver and above this, it is contradictory; containing contradictions by no means reconcileable: Such as between, <hi>Act. 9. V.</hi> 7. where it is ſaid, that the Men which were with <hi>Paul</hi> heard the voice that ſpake with him; and, <hi>Act.</hi> 22. 9. which ſaith, that they heard it not: And above a hundred ſuch, which I have collected, not to pick holes in Scripture, for they do rather confirm the Truth of it in the main, than blaſt its Authority; for it ſhews that its Pen-men did not combine together to make a formal ſtory, or they had agreed better: And why ſhould I be more offended at Chriſt as God, for ſo
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:174373:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> many faults and lies put upon him in that word, and made by the Tranſcribers; than for all the Sufferings put upon him in his Fleſh, <hi>Matth.</hi> 11. 6. I ſee him through them all, believing no more in him at the word in the Scriptures; but becauſe I know him, and could as well as others demonſtrate him to the <hi>Jews,</hi> if there were no more Scriptures left to prove him in the World. Tho' they ſerve me ſtill to do what I do here with them, <hi>viz.</hi> to confirm and to prove to thoſe that make uſe of them; the Doctrine and the Notions the inward word ſuggeſts me.</p>
            <p n="29">29. The way for a Man to know the Will and Doctrine of God, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect his ways by it according to Gods own Word; is not ſo much to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſe and to ſtudy the Scriptures, as to do the Will of Chriſt, <hi>Joh.</hi> 7. 17. that Will or Law which the Light of Nature ſhews and dictates; and to follow, and to work what it ſuggeſts to be good, as many Wiſe Heathens did. <hi>Act.</hi> 10. 2. For any Man that doth ſo is acceptable to God <hi>V. 35. and God loves him, and meets him, and makes himſelf</hi> and his Will known <hi>or manifest to him.</hi> Eſa. 64. 5. Joh. 14. 21, 23. Whilſt the Readers of the Word remain in their Ignorance and Sin; are not juſtifyed by the Sufferings of Chriſt, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2. 13. nor perconſequent by him made Wiſer or enlightned: as appears from all thoſe Sects who keep their falſe Opinions, tho' they have read, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſe, and hear the Scriptures Preached. The Will of God is, ſaith <hi>Paul, 1 Theſſ.</hi> 4. 3. our Sanctification, or that we ſhould become good; for God hath no other will but that good ſhould take place of, and overcome the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil. <hi>Rom</hi> 12. 21. which Will every Man knows by his Light without Scripture. A better Rule than Scripture to know the Will of God by, is to learn what our Will and Luſt and deſire is, and to do nothing of it, but to do, or endeavour to do, <hi>that which we would not, Ch.</hi> 7. 20. and to War and Fight always againſt our fleſhly Mind, <hi>V. 23. Ch.</hi> 8. 7. and to carry if we can, that Captivity Captive by the ſtrength of Gods Spirit, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. 16. which he gives more willingly to them that ask him in Faith, than a Father or Mother do good things to their Children, <hi>Matth. 7. 11. Luk.</hi> 11. 13.</p>
            <p n="30">30. The Scripture is poſitive that the Holy Ghoſt <hi>teacheth all things, guides into all Truth</hi> (both Natural and Divine; for the Word of Chriſt is all, and Chriſt himſelf Excepts none) <hi>ſearcheth the deep things of God, and ſhews even things to come</hi> to ſuch as are born of it: becoming <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a diſcerning Faculty, in the Soul that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives it. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5. 20. So that the Diſciples of Chriſt have no need to go to learn of any other Maſter, School, or Univerſity than of Chriſt, and his Spirit in their Heart, the inward Word. <hi>Matth.</hi> 23. 8. By him being taught of God. <hi>Joh. 6. 45. Hebr.</hi> 8. 11. all Wiſdom and all Knowledge. <hi>Col.</hi> 1. 9. And it hath been fully proved in the Eternal Goſpel (of which a Meſſenger took near 1500 Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pies) that the Holy Ghoſt is ſtill given to all the Faithful; and that in the ſame manner and meaſure as formerly to the Primitive Chriſtians, when they believe equally; that is, go from faith to faith, follow Chriſt under the Croſs in the Re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>generation or ſecond Birth of Water, in a true reſignation of their own will to God's will, as much as thoſe Chriſtians did. For man muſt be born of it (the Spirit) to be ſaved. <hi>Joh.</hi> 3. 5. and as Salvation it ſelf conſiſteth in Righteouſneſs thro the gift of that Spirit; <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. 17. all they that will be ſaved muſt have it and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it to work righteouſneſs by it; and become righteous, and ſhine in Glory, or be ſaved. <hi>Matth.</hi> 13. 43. The gift and receit of it is the fulfilling of the Promiſe made to Man through Chriſt. <hi>Luke. 24. 49. Act.</hi> 1. 4, 5. 2. 17. and this ſame Promiſe of it being made to all Mankind, it <hi>belongs</hi> to all Mankind, <hi>to us, and our Children, and to as many as God ſhall ever call,</hi> and believe. <hi>v.</hi> 39. and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:174373:11"/> ſo all men may have it, and not only what they now call its ordinary gift; but alſo all the other called extraordinary, of Healing, Tongues, Prophecy, Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, caſting out Devils, and other Signs and Miracles; if they will believe in Chriſt, and take the right way and means fit to get and obtain it, which are dying to their will, and becoming like Water, that they may be born of it: for according to St. <hi>Mark 16. 17.</hi> Chriſt ſaith poſitively ſo. And St. <hi>Peter</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firms it. <hi>Act.</hi> 10. 47. 11. 15. 15. 8. by ſaying that God gave it to the Gentiles that believed, not only <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> &amp; <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, but <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>ſecundum modum noſtrum</hi> ſaith he, in the ſame meaſure <hi>as it fell on us</hi> at firſt. And the Scriptures ſay the ſame, teaching that all the Churches of <hi>Samaria. Act. 8. 12, 16, 17. Antioch, Ch. 13, 12. Galatia Gal. 3. 2, 3, 5. Corinthus. 1 Cor 6. 11. 19. Rome 8. 11.</hi> and <hi>Theſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalonica, 2 Theſſ</hi> 2. 13. (Not only the Apoſtles, and the 120, who were all <hi>with one accord.</hi> Act. 1. 14, 15. <hi>filled with the Holy Ghost. Ch.</hi> 2. 4.) received the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt in the ſame way and meaſure as thoſe firſt believers did, <hi>Ch. 10. 46. 19. 6. Gal. 3. 5. 1 Cor. 1. 7. God putting no difference between them that purify their hearts by their Faith, and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Peter</hi> of himſelf and the other A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles. <hi>Act.</hi> 15. 9. but giving them the Spirit even as to us at firſt, in witneſs that their Faith was as ſtrong and great as ours. Thus giving it to all men: and ſealing all that believe with that Spirit of Promiſe. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. 30. and with a Portion equal to that of the Apoſtles, when they believe equally; and never permitting it to ceaſe amongſt Believers, except they ceaſe to believe. Hence the reaſon why it hath ceaſed amongſt us is plain.</p>
            <p n="31">31. I muſt here by the by take notice of theſe two things; firſt, that Mr. <hi>Keith</hi> tending to debaſe the inward word, and to extol the outward by aſcribing it the Title and Property of the firſt, calls this a Revelation, which is a giving of Sight, or taking off of a Vail, to make one ſee and perceive the Things lay hid under it; and herein he ſhews his End and Miſtake at the ſame time; for ſight, as it hath been ſhew'd, Hearing and Underſtanding, come not from the outward Word; and the Scripture it ſelf is but a Parable or Enigme, to him that hath not the Key that lets into God's Kingdom. <hi>Mark</hi> 4. 11. to wit, the Holy Spirit. <hi>Joh.</hi> 3. 5. like the Philoſophers Books of the Philoſophers Stone, where none but the Sons of Art find out the hidden Secret: and like the Revelation of St. <hi>John</hi> concerning Chriſt; which, tho' <hi>the Revelation of Chriſt,</hi> and of many things are come to paſs already. <hi>Rev.</hi> 1. 1. ſince they were to be <hi>ſhortly</hi> after they were written, yet is underſtood of none but ſuch as the Lamb of God opens the Seals of it for, <hi>Ch.</hi> 5. 5, 6. all Revelation, or Light belonging to the Spirits, which <hi>be ſends in all the Earth.</hi> If Mr. <hi>Keith,</hi> by turning Churchman had got <hi>the new Name, and the Manna promiſed.</hi> Rev. 2. 17. or were what he ſaith he is, that is, <hi>further enlightned</hi> (he ſaith ſo, <hi>pag.</hi> 14.) he would underſtand better what a Revelation is.</p>
            <p n="32">32. <hi>Secondly,</hi> to the ſame end, he makes of the Light within, (which I have declared in the 116. to be natural in all, and ſupernatural in the Regenerated) but one part of what it is, that is, the ſame, and no more than the Light of Nature is: ſaying in the 9th page, That <hi>the utmoſt extent that this Light within goeth to without Illumination, and the light of the Scripture, is no more than the Righteouſneſs of the Moral law,</hi> and terms of <hi>the first Covenant, do and live:</hi> and arguing againſt it, as taking it for granted that the Quakers make of it the ſame as he doth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, <hi>and allow no diſtinction</hi> between it and the other. (This he ſaith, <hi>pag.</hi> 11.) whereas the firſt Covenant, and the Righteouſneſs of it could never be fulfilled by all the Wit and Power comes from the Light of Nature without that by Grace in
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:174373:11"/> Chriſt. And the Quakers Practice ſhews that this is but a Cavil: For they not only pretend to more Light than all men have before they are enlightned; that is to ſay, to more than any Man hath from Nature, [but think that they are the People, <hi>Joh</hi> 12. 2. which hath engroſſed Wiſdom and God's Spirit to themſelves:] and teach that all men muſt come to their Light to be ſaved. Whereby it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears they make of their Light within much more than of the Light of Nature; and than Mr. <hi>Keith</hi> would make us believe they take it for. What their own Light really is, I will not determine. But it is a great Miſtake to allow no more to that which they call the Light within than to the Light of Nature; For the Point is not whether the Light they actually have be that they pretend to have; but if that Light which they call by the Name of Light within be that which they ſay it is; <hi>viz.</hi> above the outward Word. And what is the falſity, or the right, or the wrong of their Pretences to Truth, and to us, more than is that of ſo many other Sects, which we take no Notice of; that we ſhould be concerned againſt it for Mr. <hi>Keith?</hi> But his End is not ſo much the detecting of Errors and Lyes, as to make a Noiſe to be taken notice of; ſo any thing ſerves his Turn to build a Quarrel upon: a great Part of his Sermon, being all upon himſelf, having ſo little of his Text, that except he and his Church be the Text he preach'd upon, we may very well call it a Text without a <hi>Sermon;</hi> a <hi>Sermon</hi> without a Text; whereof the Application is to be made from <hi>Matth.</hi> 19. 27. Such is this worthy Divine's good Converſation in Chriſt!</p>
            <p n="33">33. Should he not as a Divine, have treated, <hi>exproſeſſo,</hi> of a good Converſation; What St. <hi>Peter</hi> means by it; and that it ought to be as in the preſence of God, like that of the old Seers or Believers, <hi>Elijah, 1 Kings 17. 1. Enoch. Gen. 5. 24. Noah, Ch.</hi> 6. 9. and others; <hi>Heavenly or in Heaven. Phil.</hi> 3. 20. and not upon <hi>Earthly things.</hi> V. 19. <hi>as becometh the Goſpel, Ch.</hi> 1. 27. which forbids Preachers to go from one Sect to another, or from a Poor Benefice or Pariſh to a better, but to be contented with what ſuch Sect can afford. <hi>Luk.</hi> 10. 7. and bids them to bear the Croſs. <hi>Matth.</hi> 10. 38. or to put their Will and Mind in the Sufferings of Chriſt, not into Honour and Praiſe, <hi>Joh.</hi> 5. 44. and to Fight, and help others to ſtand, Fight and overcome the Nations, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2. 26. that is, thoſe Luſts riſe and War in their Members. <hi>Jam.</hi> 4. 1. and carry the Soul Captive; and to put off the old Man, that they may put on the New, and become a New Creature. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. 23, 24. Nothing but <hi>the new Creature,</hi> and the Regeneration, which makes ſuch, <hi>avail in Chriſt.</hi> Gal. 6. 15. and to Fight and overcome, to Sanctify, Purify, and evacuate by Faith the Heart of all that fills it, is, ſaith <hi>Paul, 1 Theſſ.</hi> 4. 3. the Will of God; what he requireth of us, and would have Preachers to teach: <hi>Avoiding fooliſh Queſtions which gender nothing but Strifes.</hi> 2 Tim. 2. 23. yet of all this, very little or nothing in <hi>Keith's</hi> Sermons, but diſputes <hi>and contention (which Create a Confuſion and every evil Work.</hi> Jam. 3. 16.) for outward Ceremonies, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the outward word Regenerating of Souls; to wit, of ſuch an outward and ſuperficial new Birth, as is that which Mr. <hi>Keith</hi> is acquainted with of late. What will avail his Hearers and others at the laſt day to know his Learned Reaſons, for a ſet form of Prayers, and all the Formalities of the now Church of <hi>England?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="34">34. Surely a Man may ſerve God, work Righteouſneſs, overcome and be regenerated, without changing or turning or going from Sect to Sect; and thereby be accepted with God, as <hi>Cornelius. Act.</hi> 10. 35. and ſo be of the true Church, and of the true Religion in any Sect or Nation. And I am full perſwaded Mr. <hi>Keith</hi> had done as well in point of Converſation to ſtay a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:174373:12"/> the Quakers, or amongſt thoſe other Sects which he was a Member of before he turned Quaker; <hi>And to let his Light ſo ſhine amongſt them that they might ſee</hi> and imitate <hi>his good Works.</hi> Matth. 5. 16. as to <hi>plead for Baalim,</hi> that is, for the Lords Biſhops, and the dead and outward word againſt the Living Spirit; which they maintain hath ceaſed ſince the Primitive Chriſtians as Dr. <hi>Hicks</hi> his Sermon at St. <hi>Marys</hi> in <hi>Oxford,</hi> and the Vicar of <hi>Weſtham's</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore My Lord of <hi>London,</hi> Printed with approbation of Superiors; ſhew they do; as to Print, pag. 10 and 11. that the Word or <hi>Light within, whatſoever worth</hi> or force <hi>they may aſcribe unto it,</hi> doth not teach the Myſtery of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnation, for inſtance, to the Wiſe men, without the help of Scripture; and as to curry favour with Men, in hope of getting an equivalent to that which maketh the Prieſts Heart glad. <hi>Judg.</hi> 18. 18. 20. for St. <hi>Paul</hi> did not do ſo when he Preached the Spirit, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. 6. and hath left him a Warrant for Preaching quite otherwiſe <hi>Gal.</hi> 1. 8. Pray, if it be not lawful for the Members of your Church to rejoyn themſelves to <hi>Rome; becauſe it enjoyns many groſs er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors in its Worſhip,</hi> as you alledge in your third Sermon, pag. 25. is it not lawful for thoſe who ſee the ſame in your Church, to keep where and as they are?</p>
            <p n="25">25. If an enlightned Conſcience be the only good Conſcience (for he makes Light, pag. 6. the beſt ingredient of it) it ſeems he hath himſelf had no good Conſcience hitherto, before this laſt Turn of his; for he was not enlightned till then, as he confeſſeth, pag. 14. where he ſaith, <hi>but now with a good Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience being farther (I bleſs God) enlightned, I have declared for, and joyned in Communion with her, the Church of</hi> England. And I ſee not which way he can pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend otherwiſe; for in a Treatiſe of his, called Help in time of need, in the 54. pag. he ſaith, <hi>the word of command from the Lord which filled me with Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Joy and Comfort, came to me the 30th day of the 10th Month called</hi> Decem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, <hi>ſaying, ſhew to the People of</hi> Scotland, ſeveral particulars ſeen there, which he now unſaith: And in 78, 79. pages of the ſame, he ſaith further, <hi>and now whether ye will hear or whether ye will forbear, I declare unto you in the Name, in the Power, and in the Authority of the Living God, that the day (that's the</hi> coming of the Lord in the Spirit) <hi>is of a Truth broke up amongſt us, (Quakers) and ye ſhall look till</hi> your <hi>Eyes fail you, and rot within their holes, e're ever you ſee ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther day or appearance of Jeſus Chriſt, than what we the People of God, called Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, do wittneſs of, come.</hi> Which is a Lye in the name of the Lord with a ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance, if he be now in the right; for he now concradicts this, and a Man cannot tell Lyes, and in the name of the Lord, and yet have a good Conſcience. Alſo in his Book, call'd, Immed. Revelation, pag. 136. he ſaith, <hi>that upon this hinge,</hi> of denying the teachings and rule of the inward word, which he now denies himſelf, <hi>depends the Theology and the Clergy of that Church</hi> he now patrocinates for, making it a Lye therefore by his unſaying it now; and thus by his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying of what he had before built, makes himſelf <hi>a Tranſgreſſor,</hi> a Man of no good Conſcience, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2. 18. to get himſelf ſuch name as the Builders in <hi>Babel</hi> aimed at, and have obtain'd. <hi>Gen.</hi> 11. 4. of Builders; by deſtroying the building of other Sects; and of Hunters and Drivers of other Nations or Sects. <hi>Ch.</hi> 10. 9, 10. But what did their Policy and their Cunning amount to? Firſt they were, as all Sects are, confounded in their Language, in Doctrine and Opinion; underſtood not each other, then were ſcattered abroad, and at laſt came to nothing. And ſo will Mr. <hi>Keith</hi> do. His building of Stubble and Hay, for the Lucre of Honour and Applauſe, and earthly things;
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:174373:12"/> will prove at laſt nothing but a glorying in his own ſhame. 1 <hi>Cor. 3. 12. Phil.</hi> 3. 19. The great Drivers of the World and their Wiſdom <hi>come to nought 1 Cor. 2. 6. He that ſpeaks lyes ſhall periſh. Prov. 19. 9. Wo be to them,</hi> Mr. Keith, <hi>by whom ſuch Offences come! Matth.</hi> 18. 7.</p>
            <p n="36">36. If none but enlightned men, ſuch as <hi>have a good meaſure of true Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge</hi> (pag. 6.) have a good Conſcience indeed, the World is in a ſad Pickle, for thoſe Men being the ſame as the Regenerated, for no Man is Enlightned but by being Born again of Water and of Spirit; they are as ſcarce in the World as the Saints who go from it to the Deſarts and Mountains <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. 38. at which rate a good Conſcience is ſcarce to be found in it. But by his leave, if a Man, whether Heathen or Chriſtian, hath like St. <hi>Paul, Act. 24. 16. A Conſcience void of Offence towards God and towards Men,</hi> according to the Light he hath in him; that is to ſay, if his Light within doth not accuſe him, his Conſcience excuſeth him, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2. 15. and he hath a good Conſcience. It is ſtrange that Mr. <hi>Keith</hi> ſhould come to any new Light, and a good Conſcience therewith, by oppoſing of that Light, and turning from thoſe own it to thoſe who deny the ſame! And that he having begun by the way of the Spirit, ſhould think <hi>to be made per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect,</hi> againſt St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Opinion, <hi>Gal. 3. 3. by the Fleſh;</hi> a carnal Mind, Lip-labour, Formalities, and carnal Ordinances, which cannot make Man perfect as concerning the Conſcience. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 9. 10. Perfection or Salvation which is in the Holy Ghoſt. <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. 17. being not got by thoſe means! But they that are of the World mind the World, and end with it: and ſay any thing for it. And thus having <hi>confeſſed and come</hi> over to the Church of <hi>England, he ſhews his deeds.</hi> Act. 18. 19.</p>
            <p n="37">37. Mr. <hi>Keith,</hi> to crown his works of leſſening the Inward word, reckoneth for an Advantage accruing by the Outward that Chriſtians, by having it, enjoy the ſame Priviledge which was granted to the <hi>Jews, to have the Oracles of God,</hi> and the exceeding great and precious Promiſes, which he quotes St. <hi>Peter</hi> for, 2 <hi>Ep.</hi> 1. 4. tho' his meaning in that place being, not of the Promiſe, but of the Effect of it, to wit of the Holy Ghoſt, and of eſcaping by it the pollu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the World, to partake of the Divine Nature, and become Holy; is nothing to the purpoſe. And the <hi>Jews</hi> receiv'd it not, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 11. 39. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it was not given but ſince Chriſt was glorifyed. <hi>Joh.</hi> 7. 39. and aſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to Heaven. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. 8. And in all former Ages the Myſteries known by Chriſt were not yet made known to Man. <hi>Ch.</hi> 3. 4, 5. as in theſe laſt days where God ſpeaketh to us by his Son. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 1. 2. So that Chriſtians who en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy the effect of the Promiſe; and who may have God himſelf ſpeaking in them by his Son; have a greater Priviledge, and not the ſame as the <hi>Jews.</hi> And if they had but the ſame outward word, and God's Oracles from between the Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rubims, what ſignifies the promiſe, <hi>Iſai. 54. 13. Hebr.</hi> 8. 10, 11. of being all taught of God, ſo that they ſhould no more need to be taught of other Men; of being made Prieſts to God, <hi>Rev.</hi> 5. 10. to be able to teach themſelves, and to <hi>keep knowledge themſelves. Mal.</hi> 2. 7. and to have the Law of God written in their own Hearts. If that Law in the Heart were as he teacheth, pag. 12. but the bare <hi>tranſcript of that written in the Scriptures;</hi> and the Spirit ſerved but <hi>to ſoften</hi> the Heart of Man, the Heart would receive no more than that word it ſelf contains; whereas it can re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive more, for a Man may know all things; and thoſe other things not yet reveal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Scriptures, which Chriſt left to the Spirit. <hi>Joh.</hi> 14. 26. 16. 12, 13. and the Spirit ſearcheth all, <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. 10. even Mr. <hi>Keith</hi> himſelf. <hi>V.</hi> 15. and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecyeth this of him, Mr. <hi>Keith</hi> is Mr. <hi>Keith,</hi> and will be Mr. <hi>Keith</hi> ſtill.</p>
            <p n="38">38. Other things of the ſame ſtamp as theſe might be collected out of the three ſaid Sermons and Reaſons of Mr. <hi>Keith,</hi> and remarks made upon them: as upon all that he ſays
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:174373:13"/> about a formal worſhip, outward ſhews, Ceremonies, and all the Rites of his Church. But having been refuted by other in all Ages, I think it not worth while to trouble the Reader with them; and theſe few things ſufficing to ſhew how much the Quakers have loſt by loſing of him, and what a purchaſe he is like to prove to t'other ſide; I will only add here with St. <hi>Paul, 1 Tim. 4. 8. that bodily Exerciſe profiteth little.</hi> And that ſince the time of Chriſt, God being to be ſerved and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped in Spirit. Joh. 4. 24. <hi>and neither in this Mountain nor yet at</hi> Jeruſalem. V. 21. that is neither in this Sect nor in that Sect, Church or Temple, but any where in Spirit, in the Heart, in the Cloſet, <hi>Matth.</hi> 6. 7. between the Soul and her Spouſe; it were much to be wiſhed that Mother Church would ſet up for a Spiritual Worſhip; and that every Chriſtian ſetting it up for himſelf, would ceaſe to heap to himſelf Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers (whoſe Buſineſs it is, to turn away from the Truth, thoſe Men that have itching Ears) and to give heed to any of thoſe ſeduceing Spirits, who ſpeak in Hypocriſie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Spiritual Worſhip. 1 <hi>Tim. 4. 1. 2 Tim.</hi> 4. 3. God dwelleth no more in Temples or in Churches made with hands. <hi>Act.</hi> 7. 48. 17. 24. And will have a Spiritual Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, a Kingdom of Prieſts. <hi>Exod.</hi> 19. 6. Such as the firſt Chriſtians were. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 9. Anointed with the Spirit; that being conform to him, or Spiritual as he is; they may walk in the Spirit, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. 25. and ſerve him in the Newneſs of the Spirit that gives Life, and no more in the oldneſs of the Letter, that Killeth. <hi>Rom. 7. 6. 2 Cor.</hi> 3. 6. O Houſe of <hi>Jacob,</hi> come ye, and let us live in Spirit, and walk in the Light of God. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 2. 5. Spiritualizing of Men is the true way to Greatneſs for Preachers and Believers: and what Mr. <hi>Keith</hi> ſhould do if he would be Great indeed. <hi>Matth.</hi> 5. 19. But what he will never do, till he become in earneſt one of the Children of Light. <hi>Except our Righteousneſs exceed that of the Clergy,</hi> the Antient and Modern Scribes (for Chriſt ſpake this for all times, <hi>Mark.</hi> 13. 37. and ſo meant it of the Scribes or Clergy-Men of all times) <hi>we ſhall in no caſe, Enter into the Kingdom of God.</hi> Matth 5. 20. Wo be to us if we dont Exceed them! and whilſt we ſtand ſeeking the Law at their Mouth, and wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for their Oracles, inſtead of paſſing from them, as the Spouſe in the <hi>Canticles!</hi> 3. 4.</p>
            <p n="39">39. And truly they that argue againſt Spiritual Worſhip for the blind Ceremonies and Rites of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Church (which had not yet the Spirit <hi>Joh. 7. 39. Heb.</hi> 11. 39. what ever <hi>Keith</hi> may argue for it in his two Sermons in <hi>Bottolph-lane, May,</hi> the 12th) are no Miniſters of Chriſt; whoſe work is to ſet Men free from the Pedagogy, and the Yoak and the Bondage of Carnal Ordinances <hi>Gal.</hi> 4. 24. and bring them to Perfection. <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. 1, 2. And the State of Liberty. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 21. But of Anti-Chriſt only, who reſiſteth the Spirit that he may ſet up the Calves, and all the Works of the Fleſh, which come in with their Worſhip; and bring Man from Perfection and the Spirituality, to a Carnal ſtate again; and to the <hi>Jewiſh,</hi> Heatheniſh, and Popiſh Idolatry. For it is one of the Works of his Father the Divil <hi>Joh.</hi> 8. 44. which Chriſt is come to deſtroy. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3. 8. to bring down Spiritual things from their ſpirituality to their materiality; to a cruſt and an out-ſide; that he may vail and cover from Men their inward Subſtance; and make Man, whoſe Soul and mind is already by the fall too much turned outwardly and running on outward things, acquieſce in their out-ſide, ſhells, ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows and coverings; and to remain as he is in the ſtate he was born in, like the Colt of a wild Aſs. <hi>Joh</hi> 11. 12. a Beaſt that never attempts to riſe up to Light and Life. O how happy were Mankind if they had no ſuch Prieſts! Or if he were not by them compell'd to become a Beaſt! <hi>Beſtiae ſint beſtiae ſed ſinant beſtiae hominem homo eſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="40">40. Mr. <hi>Keith</hi> hath juſtified himſelf enough before Men; but God when he judgeth Men, will ſhew whether he be Wiſe. <hi>Dan.</hi> 12. 3. This I will ſay for him, he is as wiſe as he was when of the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> or <hi>Quaker Church</hi> or <hi>Party;</hi> but that a good <hi>Biſhoprick</hi> would much Clarify his Head; or make of him a <hi>Virum Clariorem</hi> than he is; the Mitre, which is ſhaped like the flames it betokeneth <hi>Act.</hi> 2. 3. having a ſtrange Energy from its configuration, in bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of obſcure heads. And I will lay with him that, for all the Enlightning he hath newly received by becoming a Church-Man, he cannot give an Account of the Neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity and Reaſons why Chriſt, <hi>being very God of very God,</hi> left his Glory and died: tho' I have ſaid enough of that here in this Paper, to ſhew him, and direct him how to find out this Enigme.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:174373:13"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
